<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Merritt Smith's blog</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 04:36:16 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 04:36:16 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rothko: A Set of Color Palettes for R</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Rothko&lt;/span&gt;  is a set of color palettes for R in the form of an R package. It follows directly from Karthik Ram’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/karthik/wesanderson&quot;&gt;wesanderson&lt;/a&gt; package, but instead using color palettes derived from Mark Rothko’s paintings. I did this with &lt;a href=&quot;https://imagemagick.org/index.php&quot;&gt;ImageMagick&lt;/a&gt;, but there’s many websites out there that will do the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s simple to install, and has options for both continuous and discrete data. Install it using &lt;code&gt;devtools::install_github(&quot;mmerrittsmith/rothko&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The palettes are named after the paintings they are derived from, and this leads to some having rather long names like “Violet, Black, Orange, Yellow on White and Red”. Others are named simply “Unitled 1949”. My personal favorites are shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rothko_palette(&quot;Number 10&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Number 10&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Number10-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rothko_palette(&quot;Light Cloud, Dark Cloud&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Light Cloud, Dark Cloud&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/LightCloudDarkCloud-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rothko_palette(&quot;Number 16&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Number 16&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/Number16-1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use these palettes in the same way that you would use any palette in R, for example as an argument to &lt;code&gt;scale_fill_gradientn&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 12:30:27 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/21/Rothko-Color-Palettes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/21/Rothko-Color-Palettes</guid>
        
        
        <category>r</category>
        
        <category>rothko</category>
        
        <category>generative</category>
        
        <category>art</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>George H. Bush:Mikhail Gorbachev :: Magnus Carlsen:Fabiano Caruana</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;Chess for geopolitics&lt;/span&gt;  is an overworked metaphor. It seems to be capturing the way in which geopolitics is a game played by the people in high towers, combining a war from the tactictal to the operational to the strategic with a staring contest between two equavalently equipped opponents. Leaving aside the many aspects of geopolitics that are emphatically not well reflected in chess, I don’t find even these aspects to be universally available in geopolitics. However, in the specific case of the Cold War, maybe it’s not so bad. &lt;!--more--&gt;In that case, it captures the way in which the two sides peered at each other over the chessboard of Europe, the dichotomy between the two in the white and black pieces. The metaphor takes on a much more direct meaning due to Soviet prowess in the form of Tal, Spassky, Botvinnik, and Petrosian&lt;label for=&quot;Soviet-grandmasters&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Soviet-grandmasters&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;By no means an exhaustive list, a complete list of Soviet chess legends would be an impressive if boring blog post &lt;/span&gt; being challenged by the American &lt;label for=&quot;Fischer-hates-authority&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Fischer-hates-authority&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;At the time &lt;/span&gt; Bobby Fischer. The old world legends upstaged by the brash young American. The stories wrote themselves. Of course, Soviets quickly reclaimed the top spot and held onto it for quite a while thanks to Karpov and Kasparov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One commonality between board games, war games, politics, and relationships is the learned skill of picking your battles. &lt;label for=&quot;militaristic-turns-of-phrase&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;militaristic-turns-of-phrase&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Not dying on this hill. Living to fight another day. Militaristic aphorisms abound. &lt;/span&gt; A number of events in the past few weeks all related to this idea have blended together in my head. When listening to the episode of John Dickerson”s wonderful Whistlestop podcast entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2018/12/berlin-wall-1989-critics-president-george-h-w-bush-wasnt-saying-enough.html&quot;&gt;If a Wall Falls&lt;/a&gt;, I thought about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Kasparov63/status/1067125702712004609&quot;&gt;criticism&lt;/a&gt; that Magnus Carlsen received for not pressing his &lt;a href=&quot;https://lichess.org/analysis/standard/r3brk1/1pq5/3p1bp1/2nP1p1p/pQP1pP1P/4B1P1/PPR1BN2/1K1R4_w_-_-&quot;&gt;.9 centipawn advantage&lt;/a&gt; and superior position in Game 12 of the World Chess Championship, and how that compared to George H. Bush”s decision to not crow his victory as the Berlin Wall fell.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;fullwidth&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/battleofcannae.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The Battle of Cannae in two images. Hannibal presented a weak center to the Romans, who responded with a deep formation to press this advantage. The Carthaginian forces then enveloped the Romans in one of the worst Roman defeats ever. A parable about the value of restraint.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither the Berlin Wall falling nor Carlsen’s advantageous position meant guaranteed victory, though we may now see them as inevitable due to the true course of history. As Dickerson notes in his podcast, there were a number of uncertainties surrounding Gorbachev and the trajectory of the Soviet Union under him. No one knew for certain whether he was a good faith reformer, and even if he was, no one knew whether the path to reform would be altered by the “hard-liners in Moscow”. Bush took Gorbachev at his word as a reformer, and purposefully assisted him by not giving fodder to the more conservative Soviet leaders. This ultimately proved to be the right decision, as the dissolution of the USSR occurred without any shots being fired between the two major powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen also elected not to press his advantage in Game 12 against Caruana. There is some very clear strategy behind this choice. Carlsen, the #1 player in the world in all three time constraints of chess&lt;label for=&quot;types-of-chess&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;types-of-chess&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Classical, Rapid, and Blitz &lt;/span&gt;, has an Elo score of 2835 in Classical format, while Caruana has an Elo score of 2832 in Classical. An insignificant difference. However, Carlsen has an Elo score of 2903 in Rapid format, while Caruana has an Elo score of 2766 in Rapid format. Using &lt;a href=&quot;https://wismuth.com/elo/calculator.html#name1=Carlsen%2C+Magnus&amp;amp;name2=Caruana%2C+Fabiano&amp;amp;best_of=12&quot;&gt; this calculation &lt;/a&gt; of their win probabilities based on their ratings, Magnus had about a 43% chance of winning in 12 classical games, Caruana had a 39% chance of winning, and there was a 19% chance of a draw after 12. In the Rapid best of 4 tiebreaker, Magnus had a 78% chance of winning, Caruana had a 6% chance of winning, and there was a 15% chance of a draw, based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://wismuth.com/elo/calculator.html#best_of=4&amp;amp;rating1=2903&amp;amp;rating2=2766&quot;&gt;this calculation&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not hard to see why Carlsen elected to draw and move on to the tiebreaker. The wisdom of this choice was born out by Carlsen’s three successive victories under Rapid time constraints.&lt;label for=&quot;carlsenraps&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;carlsenraps&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;Also it has come to my attention that Carlsen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=380&amp;amp;v=ahtbecpKtOg&quot;&gt;rapped&lt;/a&gt; on a song by Mr. Pimp-Lotion a few days ago, and it is my ethical responsibility to pass the happiness it brought me along &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no need to raise your risk profile&lt;label for=&quot;daryl-morey&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;daryl-morey&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Shoutout to Daryl Morey &lt;/span&gt; when you have the advantage. This is not to say that sitting on your hands is the best policy, only that perhaps the greatest advantage of having the advantage is the ability to pick your battles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 12:24:46 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/18/George-Bush-Mikhail-Gorbachev-Magnus-Carlsen-Fabiano-Caruana</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/18/George-Bush-Mikhail-Gorbachev-Magnus-Carlsen-Fabiano-Caruana</guid>
        
        
        <category>chess</category>
        
        <category>history</category>
        
        <category>geopolitics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Partial Dependence Plots in Python</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;newthought&quot;&gt;In writing my undergrad thesis&lt;/span&gt;  on wealth inequality and using various techniques for predicting it, I found myself disappointed that there was no simple method in Python’s scikit-learn to generate partial dependence plots for random forests. The ability to create partial dependence plots for gradient boosted regressors &lt;a href=&quot;https://scikit-learn.org/stable/auto_examples/ensemble/plot_partial_dependence.html&quot;&gt;exists&lt;/a&gt;, so why not for random forests, or anything else for that matter? In this post, I’ll discuss partial dependence plots, what they are, how they’re useful in ensemble methods, and dive into the state of the art for partial dependence plots in Python.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-a-partial-dependence-plot&quot;&gt;What’s a partial dependence plot?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A partial dependence plot is an attempt to open up the black box of ensemble methods. Normally, we can compute the importance of a given variable in estimating the response varaible, but do not have a great intuition as to the decision surface of even the most important variables. Partial dependence plots allow us to see the marginal effect of a given variable on the response variable by integrating out all of the other variables. They allow us to see the effect of a single variable on the response variable, which is otherwise not possible in ensemble methods. Thus, they’re a very powerful tool. Some say ensemble methods are being left by the wayside in 2018 for ever more complicated neural nets, but ensemble methods continue to provide a powerful and much more interpretable option for both regression and classification thanks to partial dependence plots. Also, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1610.01271.pdf&quot;&gt;recent research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that with some alterations ensemble methods can be used for treatment effect estimation, which is an extremely promising line of inquiry to me. Now let’s see what they look like!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;state-of-the-code-python&quot;&gt;State of the code: Python&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s been &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scikit-learn/scikit-learn/issues/4405&quot;&gt;motion&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scikit-learn/scikit-learn/pull/5653&quot;&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scikit-learn/scikit-learn/pull/12599&quot;&gt;the topic&lt;/a&gt; of partial dependence plots since 2015 within sklearn, as well as some external work by a number of sources on creating a generalized partial dependence plot library&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; that can connect to the extant classifiers and regressors. I decided to test each of these tools out. The sklearn partial dependence plot is still going through edits, but it performs admirably, creating simple R-style partial dependence plot matrices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Partial Dependence Plots of fixed acidity and volatile acidity on perceived wine quality using data from UCI Machine Learning Repository Wine Quality Dataset.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/SklearnPDP.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The code also extends easily to create three dimensional partial dependence plots, should that tickle your fancy. Not normally my cup of tea, but in this case it allows for a more pithy data visualization and efficiently demonstrates variable interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;3D Partial Dependence Plot of fixed acidity and volatile acidity on perceived wine quality using data from UCI Machine Learning Repository Wine Quality Dataset,
specifically using white wine portion. &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/SklearnPDP3D.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, this tool, if implemented, would be integrated seamlessly into the most commonly used Python machine learning library and would be a plotting option for every single ensemble method within sci-kit learn. That’s big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more established and feature-rich Python library for plotting partial dependence is the NYU Visualization Lab’s ‘partial_dependence’. It offers an abstraction of matplotlib with its pdp_plot object, with which you can calculate partial dependence, clusters, and plot. I’m particularly a fan of the automated clustered pdp plot with full curves. Since I’m using random forests for each of these examples, I get a slightly jittery plot, but this plot is very easy to create and effectively demonstrates the partial dependence of the a wine’s density on its score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A PDP created with the NYU Visualization Lab partial_dependence library, classifying good and bad wine using with the sklearn RandomForestClassifier. The options used to create this plot were cell_view = True, plot_full_curves = True, local_curves = False.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/nyupdp.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, PDPbox. It also supports As of typing this, the pdp_interact_plot functionality appeared to be broken for the default option, contour plots, due to a recent change in matplotlib. In fact, there are a number of functionalities that aren’t working as expected due to changes in other packages, so if using this packages keep that in mind. The implementation for creating simple PDPs in this package is through pdp_plot, which is what I use below to look at the effect of the pH of the wine on the quality. It’s fairly feature-rich, allowing you to select whether to cluster, how to cluster, how many lines to show, etc. all in one function call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;A PDP created with PDPbox, classifying good and bad wine using with the sklearn RandomForestClassifier. This is an example of the PDPBox PDPIsolate and pdp_plot functionality.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/pdpbox.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, all of these libraries are great options for creating tasetful and informative partial dependence plots. It comes down to the degree of extendability and aesthetics. If you want a package that is supported by the biggest machine learning library in Python, follow the threads on the SklearnPDP pull request. If you like the stylistics of the NYU partial_dependence package and would like a lot of the matplotlib details abstracted away, it’s a fantastic option. If your ideal partial dependence plot is more professional-looking, give PDPbox a whirl. Like a kid in a candy shop, you can’t go wrong, it’s all about preferences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 14:30:27 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/18/Partial-Dependence-Plots-in-Python</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/18/Partial-Dependence-Plots-in-Python</guid>
        
        
        <category>python</category>
        
        <category>r</category>
        
        <category>sklearn</category>
        
        <category>randomforest</category>
        
        <category>ensemble</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
